A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Books and Reports Department, Special Items FA936
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Books and Reports Department, Special Items
1965-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University Press
FA936
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box.
1 box.
Biographical/Historical note
In order to assist in the dissemination of scientific investigations conducted at the Institute and elsewhere, publication was an early and important activity of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. A senior member of the scientific staff was usually the editor of a periodical. As early as 1910 the Institute had a Publication Service, which was supervised from 1910 by Editha C. Campbell until she retired in the fall of 1940. A Department of Illustration and Photography was under a part-time arrangement with De. Eduard Learning from 1906 until 1910 when Louis Schmidt undertook the direction of a full-time department. Louis Schmidt was at the head of the department until he reached the age of 70 in 1936. The work in the Department of Illustrations included hand-drawn illustrations for publications, photographs, moving pictures of experimental procedures made for the various investigators and used for a variety of purposes. Louis Schmidt served on a consultant basis until his death in 1939. Joseph Blauvelt Haulenbeek was acting in charge of Illustrations during that time and named officially in charge of illustrations in 1942, serving until he resigned September 1, 1946. Julian Alexander Carlile who was in charge of illustrations in the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology at Princeton took charge of the New York Department starting October 1, 1947 and divided his time between the two departments until they were consolidated during 1950. He directed the expanding department until his death in 1959 when he was succeeded by Richard F. Carter until 1964. In the academic year 1968/1969 Lewis William Koster became Manager of Graphic Services until 1973. March 1973 Bill Leyrer was appointed to that position.
Florence M. Stewart succeeded Editha Campbell in charge of the Publication Service in 1940 and served until she retired June 30, 1963, when she was succeeded by Margaret E. Broadbent.
Effective January 1, 1957 Charles Irvin Campbell was appointed Administrative Associate for Information Services. He had responsibility for a variety of information services among which were Secretary of the Library Committee, Librarian, ex officio, and supervision of the Publication Service and Illustration and Duplicating Services. Included were publication duties of such items as the Annual Report, Rockefeller Institute Quarterly, and the Calendar of Events. On October 20, 1958 the Board of Trustees approved a cooperative arrangement with the Oxford University Press to assist in producing, advertising and selling publications of the newly established Rockefeller Institute Press. The plan was for the Institute to continue publishing journals in accord with previously established policy and arrangements. Charles I. Campbell was appointed Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. The Publications Service became the Journals Department without change of personnel or function. A new Books and Reports Department was created with responsibility for the production of books and the publication of bulletins and reports issued by the Institute.
January 1, 1960 Reynard F. Biemiller was appointed Assistant Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. Effective December 5, 1960 Raymond B. Griffiths was appointed to the newly created position of Executive Editor of the Journal of Cell Biology.
Charles I. Campbell resigned May 15, 1962 and Joseph G. Sutton served as Acting Director of the Press from January 1963 until in 1964 William Arthur Bayless was named Director of the Press.
William Bayless retired as Director of The Rockefeller University Press on February 8, 1980. As of February 11, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan agreed to serve as acting director of the Press.
Effective July 1, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan was appointed Director of The Rockefeller University Press.
Scope and Contents
"Special Items" are a collection of items printed and designed in the Rockefeller University Press for special purposes or special events.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 531
Medical sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Life sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Biology -- Research; Science -- Study and teaching; Medical education; Medical technology; Medical research
- Flier "Law and the Social Role of Science", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Flier "The Scientific Endeavor", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlet "Three Centuries of Botany in North America" an exhibit celebrating the publication of WILD FLOWERS OF THE UNITED STATES, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Complimentary preprint and pamphlet THE NEUROSCIENCES: A STUDY PROGRAM, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlet "AAAS Michael Faraday Exhibit at RU", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Flier "Scientific writing for Graduate Students", 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlet "Behavioral Science Rockefeller University", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlet "Illustration Standards for Rockefeller University", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pamphlet "Press Journals", 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Price list and description of University Press publications, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Press Release on publication of "The Great Adventure", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Items on the retirement of Reynard Biemiller (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NEWS AND NOTES, 1975 October
  - BIEMILLERANA, booklet in honor of R. Biemiller, printed and bound by The Harbor Press
  - Tape made at retirement party
  - 2 biographical notes from Library exhibit
- Advertising and order form, 1976; 3 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Griffin, Donald R. THE QUESTION OF ANIMAL AWARENESS, 1976
- Advertising and order form, 1976; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - THE ROCKEFELLER UNIVERSITY FILMS (on primate behavior), 1976; 4 16 mm. films
  - THE ROCKEFELLER UNIVERSITY COUNCIL 8 page pamphlet (includes list), 1976
- Advertising and order form, 1976; 3 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dubos, R. THE PROFESSOR, THE INSTITUTE AND DNA, 1976
- Advertising and order form, 1976; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - FIRST TIME ON MICROFILM: complete backfiles; standing subs, 1976
- Subscriptions and complete backfiles, 1978; microfilm and microfiche (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Journal of experimental medicine, 1978
  - Journal of general physiology, 1978
  - Journal of clinical investigation, 1978
  - Journal of cell biology, 1978
  - Biophysical journal, 1978
  - Listing of the available numbers with order # and price, 1978; 2 copies
  - "The Rockefeller University Press Publications", 1978; Pamphlet 20 pp.
- JOURNALS OF THE ROCKEFELLER UNIVERSITY PRESS, 1979
  - Advertising (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Another book of interest. The Professor, the Institute, and DNA. Oswald T. Avery, 1979; 2 copies
    - HERACLITEAN FIRE, by Erwin Chargaff, 1979; 2 copies
      Scope and Contents note
      This is a complimentary presentation copy.
    - HERACLITEAN FIRE. Sketches from a life before Nature Erwin Chargaff, 1979; 2 copies
      From The Rockefeller University Press.
    - HERACLITEAN FIRE. Sketches from a life before nature Erwin Chargaff, 1979; 2 copies, 4 pp.
  - Pamphlets (Box 1)
    - Abby Aldreich Rockefeller Hall. Description of facilities and services available on campus for visitors, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The future of biomedical research and education. Four talks on the occasion of the installation of Dr. Joshua Lederberg as President of The Rockefeller University, 1978 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Rockefeller University "An Introduction", 1980; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes map of campus
    - "Journals of the Rockefeller University Press 1980", 11 pp. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "A Special Place", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Rockefeller University Press Journals 1981" (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "The Rockefeller University Council", 1982 November; [pamphlet] (Box 1, Folder 7)